William F. Fullam Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William F. Fullam Papers 1873-1942 1906-1922
MSS50096
Fullam, William F. (William Freeland), 1855-1926
3,850 items
10 containers
3 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officer and journalist. Correspondence, bulletins, biographical data, naval news sheets, radio dispatches, reports, orders, commissions, transcripts of congressional testimony, writings, photographs, clippings, and other records relating to Fullam's naval career.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Benson, William Shepherd, 1855-1932.; Borah, William Edgar, 1865-1940.; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948.; Fullam, William F. (William Freeland), 1855-1926.; Mitchell, William, 1879-1936.; Schumann-Heink, Ernestine, 1861-1936.
Organizations
United States. Navy--Aviation.; United States. Navy--Foreign service--Caribbean Area.; United States. Navy--Foreign service--West Indies.; United States. Navy--Reorganization.
Subjects
Spanish-American War, 1898--Campaigns--Cuba.; Spanish-American War, 1898--Naval operations, American.
Places
Caribbean Area--History, Naval.
Occupations
Journalists.; Naval officers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of William F. Fullam, naval officer and journalist, were deposited in the Library of Congress in 1952 by the Naval Historical Foundation and converted to a gift in 1998.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William F. Fullam are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1855, Oct. 20 Born, Pittsford, N.Y.
1877 Graduated, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1879 1883 Duty on the Swatara, Asiatic Station
1883 1887 Instructor, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1885 Married Mariana W. Robinson
1886 Promoted to lieutenant
1887 1891 Duty on the Boston (sloop of war), Yorktown, and Chicago
1891 1894 Instructor, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1894 1897 Duty on the Raleigh and Amphitrite
1898 Duty on the New Orleans, Spanish-American War Instructor at United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1899 Published Handbook for Infantry and Artillery, United States Navy. Annapolis, Md.: Naval Institute
1900 1902 Executive officer, Lancaster (sloop of war)
1902 Published The Recruit’s Handy Book. Annapolis, Md.: Naval Institute Published The Petty Officer’s Drill Book. Annapolis, Md.: Naval Institute
1902 1904 Instructor, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1905 Commanded the Terror and the Glacier Promoted to commander
1906 1907 Commanded the Marietta (gunboat) during Cuban, Caribbean, and Central American politico-military actions
1907 1909 Commanded the Naval Training Station, Newport, R.I.
1909 Promoted to captain
1909 1911 Commanded the Mississippi (battleship)
1911 1913 Commandant, Naval Training Station, Great Lakes, III.
1914 Promoted to rear admiral
1914 1915 Superintendent, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1915 1917 Commander in chief, United States Pacific Reserve Fleet
1917 1919 Commander, Patrol Force, United States Pacific Fleet
1919 Retired from the United States Navy
1926, Sept. 23 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Freeland Fullam (1855-1926) span the years 1873-1942, with the bulk of the material falling in the period 1906-1922. The papers consist of correspondence, orders to duty, speeches and writings, newspaper clippings, printed matter, photographs, and miscellaneous items and are organized into the following series: General Correspondence and Orders to Duty, Speech, Article, and Book File, and Miscellany.
Fullam’s correspondence and the columns he wrote for the New York Tribune in the 1920s reflect his views on the removal of United States marines from cruising ships, the reorganization of the Navy Department and the coordination of its bureaus, the superiority of air power, the conduct of World War I operations, and other military topics.
The papers also provide insight into American foreign policy in the Caribbean and Central American areas where Fullam had patrolled the coastal waters of Santo Domingo, Cuba, Honduras, and Nicaragua in 1906 and 1907.
Prominent among Fullam’s correspondents are Philip Andrews, William S. Benson, Victor Blue, Josephus Daniels, Edwain Denby, George Dewey, Bradley A. Fiske, Albert Gleaves, Ernestine Schumann-Heink, Harris Laning, Blair Lee, Stephen B. Luce, Charles B. McVay, William A. Mitchell, James H. Oliver, John E. Pillsbury, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Seaton Schroeder, William S. Sims, and Richard Wainwright.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
General Correspondence and Orders to Duty, 1877-1926
Speech, Article, and Book File, 1893-1924
Miscellany, 1873-1942
Container List
- General Correspondence and Orders to Duty, 1877-1926 (Box 1-6)
  Letters received and drafts of letters sent.
  Arranged by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Letters received and drafts of letters sent (Box 1)
    - 1883-1907, Mar. (Box 1)
    - 1907, Apr.-Aug. (Box 2)
    - 1908, Sept.-1916. Apr. (Box 3)
    - 1916, May-1917, Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1918-1920 (Box 5)
    - 1921-1926 (Box 6)
  - Orders to duty, 1877-1914 (Box 6)
- Speech, Article, and Book File, 1893-1924 (Box 7-8)
  Articles, historical sketches, notes, reports, statements, and miscellaneous items.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Articles (Box 7)
    - Copies of articles and speeches, typewritten, 1917-1918, undated (Box 7)
    - Magazine clippings, 1894-1923 (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 7)
      - By or about Fullam, 1919-1923, undated (Box 7)
      - Published by Fullam in the New York Tribune under his pseudonym "Quarterdeck," 1920-1922 (Box 7)
  - Congressional and official statements and reports (Box 7)
    - Senate Subcommittee of the Committee on Naval Affairs, 1920 (Box 7)
    - United States Congress Aircraft Investigating Committee, 1924 (Box 7)
    - United States Navy Board on the bombing of German ships, undated (Box 7)
    - Withdrawal of marines from cruising ships, 1893-1913 (Box 7)
  - Historical data (1915-1919) and reports on the United States Pacific Fleet (Box 8)
  - Historical sketch (1844-1906) and reports on Santo Domingo (Box 8)
  - Holograph notes and preface for an unpublished book, “Three Plane Navy” (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 8)
  - Notes on the Battle of Tsushima (Box 8)
  - Photostatic copies of data prepared for the United States Congress on “Treaty Navies,” listing statistics on the navies of the United States, Great Britain, and Japan 1924 (Box 8)
  - Typewritten manuscript of an unpublished essay, “Campaign of 1812" (Box 8)
- Miscellany, 1873-1942 (Box 9-10)
  Biographical material, photographs, printed matter, and other miscellaneous items.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material.
  - Biographical file, undated (Box 9)
  - Commissions, 1873-1914 (Box 9)
  - Newspaper clippings and printed matter, 1892-1942 (Box 9)
  - Photographs, 1876-1925 (Box 10)